Edward Grant papers, 1950-2001 C184
Indiana University Archives
- Publications, 1961-2001
  - Reviews, 1961-1998
    - Jordanus de Nemore. Review of De Numeris Datis. Translated by Barnabas Bernard Hughes. Reviewed in Historia Mathematica,: 125-129., (1983) (Box 17)
    - Olson, Richard. Review of Science Deified and Science Defied: The Historical Significance of Science in Western Culture from the Bronze Age to the Beginnings of the Modern Era ca. 3500 B.C. to ca. A. D. 1640. Reviewed in Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences 39,: 88-89., (Jan. 1984) (Box 17)
    - Ferruolo, Stephen C. Review of The Origins of the University: The Schools of Paris and their Critics, 1100-1215. Reviewed in History of Education Quarterly 26, no. 3:435-437., (Fall 1986) (Box 17)
    - Hansen, Bert, ed. Review of Nicole Oresme and the Marvels of Nature: A Study of His "De Causis Mirabilium" with Critical Edition, Translation, and Commentary. Reviewed in Isis 77, no. 286:186-187., (1986) (Box 17)
    - Jardine, Nicholas. Review of The Birth of History and Philosophy of Science: Kepler's "A Defence of Tycho against Ursus" with Essays on its Provenance and Significance. Reviewed in Journal for the History of Astronomy 17, part 2,: 137-140., (May 1986) (Box 17)
    - Pedersen, Fritz Saaby, ed. Review of Philomena de Dacia and Petrus de Sancto Audomaro, Opera Quadrivialia, 1: Opera Petri Philomenae; 2. Opera Petri de Sancto Audomaro. Reviewed in Speculum 61, :248., (1986) (Box 17)
    - Review of Burley on Motion in a Vacuum, 1987 (Box 17)
    - Duhem, Pierre. Review of Medieval Cosmology: Theories of Infinity, Place, Time Void, and the Plurality of Worlds. Reviewed in Speculum 62, no. 4:927-929., (Oct. 1987) (Box 17)
    - Gottfried. Review of Medieval Science and Society, 1987 (Box 17)
    - Pflanze. Review of The Impact of Money..., 1987 (Box 17)
    - North, John D. Review of Chaucer's Universe. Reviewed in Journal for the History of Astronomy 21,: 215-217., (1990) (Box 17)
    - Cobban, Alan B. Review of The Medieval English Universities: Oxford and Cambridge to c. 1500. Reviewed in Libraries & Culture, a Journal of Library History 25, no. 2:276-277., (Spring 1990) (Box 17)
    - Review of Oresme and Relativity of Motion., 1990 (Box 17)
    - Kieckhefer, Richard. Review of Magic in the Middle Ages. Reviewed in American Historical Review 96,: 853-854., (June 1991) (Box 17)
    - Dahlstrom, Daniel D., ed. Review of Nature and Scientific Method Reviewed in The Review of Metaphysics.,: 149-151., (Sept. 1992) (Box 17)
    - Review of Oresme and Ratios of Lesser Inequality, 1991 (Box 17)
    - Iorio, Dominick A. Review of The Aristotelians of Renaissance Italy, A Philosophical Exposition. Reviewed in Isis 84, (1993) (Box 17)
    - de Ridder-Symoens, Hilde, ed. Review of A History of the University in Europe. Reviewed in History of Education Quarterly 33, no. 3: 395-398., (Fall 1993) (Box 17)
    - Unpublished review for Technology and Culture, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Schmitt. Review of Experience and Experiment., undated (Box 17)
  - Files related to Grant's book Nicole Oresme: "De Proportionibus Proportionum" and "Ad Pauca Respicientes", published in., 1966 (Box 18)
    - Changes in volume, 1963-1965 (Box 18)
    - Plates, 1963-1965 (Box 18)
    - Proof Sheets, 1960 (Box 18)
    - Review of volume, 1966 (Box 18)
  - Files related to Grant's book Physical Science in the Middle Ages, published in, 1977
    - Hardbound copy of book, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Copy of Japanese translation, 1982 (Box 18)
    - Review of Physical Science, undated (Box 18)
  - Files related to Grant's book Nicole Oresme and the Kinematics of Circular Motion, published in, 1971
    - Manuscript, 1971; (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Review of volume, 1971 (Box 18)
  - Files related to Grant's book A Source Book in Medieval Science, published in, 1981
    Volume II of manuscript is missing.
    - Permissions (Box 18)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 18)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 18)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 18)
      - (from Wisc. Univ. Press), undated (Box 18)
    - Material for Source Book, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Selections to be typed, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Topics, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Manuscript of Source Book Vol. I (Box 18)
      - (preface-pg. 54), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 55-186), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 187-271mm), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 277-416), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 417-481), 1974 (Box 18)
    - Vol. III (there is no Vol. II) (Box 18)
      - (pg. 1013-1116), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 1117-1216), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 1217-1324), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 1325-1408), 1974 (Box 18)
      - (pg. 1409-1497), 1974 (Box 18)
    - Vol. IV (Box 19)
      - (pg. 1498-1664), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 1665-1784), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 1785-1908), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 1909-2043), 1974 (Box 19)
    - Vol. V (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2044-2175), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2176-2299), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2300-2407), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2408-2537), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2538-2622), 1974 (Box 19)
      - (pg. 2623-2748), 1974 (Box 19)
    - Errors in Source Book, undated (Box 19)
    - Review of volume, 1976 (Box 19)
  - Files related to Grant's book Much Ado About Nothing: Theories of Space and Vacuum from the Middle Ages to the Scientific Revolution, published in, 1981
    - Preface, undated (Box 19)
    - Edited page proofs, undated; (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Review of volume, undated (Box 19)
  - Files related to Grant's work In Defense of the Earth's Centrality..., Varorium Reprints, published in, 1984
    - Studies in Medieval Science (indexed articles), 1981; (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Review of volume, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Files related to Grant's book Mathematics and its Applications to Science and Natural Philosophy in the Middle Ages published in, 1987
    - Materials for volume, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Line figures, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Review, 1987 (Box 19)
  - Files related to Grant's book Planets, Stars, & Orbs: The Medieval Cosmos, 1200-1687 published in, 1994
    - NEH Publication: Planets, Stars, Orbs, 1992-1993 (Box 19)
    - The Medieval Cosmos (Book), 1976 (Box 19)
    - Medieval Cosmos, Chapters 1 & 2, 1988 (Box 19)
    - Review of volume, undated (Box 19)
    - Copy of volume, 1994 (Box 19)
  - Files related to Grant's book The Foundations of Modern Science in the Middle Ages, published in, 1996
    - Edited galley sheets, 1996; (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Copy of book, 1996 (Box 20)
  - Files related to Grant's book God and Reason in the Middle Ages, published in, 2001
    - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 20)
    - Manuscript (Box 20)
      - (pg. 1-127), 2001 (Box 20)
      - (pg. 128-279), 2001 (Box 20)
      - (pg. 280-421), 2001 (Box 20)
      - (pg. 422-578), 2001 (Box 20)
      - (pg. 579-end), 2001 (Box 20)
- Professional Activities, 1958-1997
  - Professional Associations, 1966-1997
    - Academie Internationale D'Histoire des Sciences (Box 20)
      - 1966-1984, (2 folders) (Box 20)
      - (correspondence), 1967-1972; 1989-1991 (Box 20)
    - American Academy of Arts & Sciences (Box 20)
      - 1982-1991 (Box 20)
      - undated (Box 20)
      - (Midwest Center correspondence), 1991-1998 (Box 20)
      - (Midwest Center general), 1991-1998 (Box 20)
    - Association of Members of the Institute of Advanced Study (AMIAS), 1975; 1982-1986 (Box 20)
    - History of Science Society (Box 20)
      - (Pfizer Comm.), 1972; 1975 (Box 20)
      - Corresp. relating to Grant's Vice Presidency (Box 20)
        - Jan-Feb 1983 (Box 20)
        - Mar-Apr 1983, 1984 (Box 20)
      - Vice-Presidential business, 1983 (Box 20)
      - Corresp. relating to Grant's Presidency, 1985-1986 (Box 20)
      - Council meeting, 1985 (Box 20)
      - Lilly Exhibit for HSS, 1985 (Box 20)
      - Executive committee meeting (Box 20)
        - Fall 1986 (Box 20)
        - Corresp. relating to above, 12 Nov 1985; Feb-Nov 1986 (Box 20)
      - Pittsburgh meeting, 1986 (Box 20)
      - committee appointments for, 1986 (Box 20)
      - Quincentennial of Discovery of Am., Nov 1985-Jan 1986 (Box 20)
      - Council meeting, 1986 (Box 20)
      - Communications, 1989-1990 (Box 20)
      - Madison banquet, 1 Nov 1991 (Box 21)
      - Madison meeting, 2 Nov 1991 (Box 21)
      - Corresp. relating to Madison Celebration, 1991 (Box 21)
      - Sarton Medal, 1992 (Box 21)
      - General, 1997 (Box 21)
    - XIth International Congress of the History of Science, 24-29 Aug 1965 (Box 21)
    - Medieval Academy of America, 1988-1992 (Box 21)
    - U.S. Nat'l Committee of the Intern'l Union of the History... (USNC/IUHPS) (Box 21)
      - 1964, 1967-1969; (2 folders) (Box 21)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 21)
  - Professional committees, 1969-1996
    - All-University committee, 1973 (Box 21)
    - Concerned Titled Professors of IU, 1988 (Box 21)
    - Distinguished Ranks Comm., 1989-1990; 1993 (Box 21)
    - Faculty Discussion Club, 1971-1972 (Box 21)
    - Field Review Comm. for Medieval European History, 1970-1975 (Box 21)
    - Harvard--Overseer's Committee, 1991; (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Harvard, Committee to visit, 1994-1996 (Box 21)
    - IMU Portrait Gallery Comm., 1988-1990; 1993 (Box 21)
    - Institute for Advanced Study--IU, 1982-1986 (Box 21)
    - Review of Dept.--Univ. of Oklahoma, 1993 (Box 21)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Gamma, 1995 (Box 21)
    - Univ. of Pittsburgh--Appraisal, Mar 1979 (Box 21)
    - Univ. of Toronto--Appraisal, 1969; (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Inst., 7 Dec 1985 (Box 21)
  - Lectures, 1958-2000
    - IU Dept. of History, 31 Oct 1958 (Box 21)
    - Purdue Univ., 18 Feb 1960 (Box 21)
    - Alumni Institute, 3 Jun 1960 (Box 21)
    - Voice of America, Oct 1962 (Box 21)
    - Denver Talk, 29 Nov 1962 (Box 21)
    - XIIth International--Paris, Aug 1968 (Box 21)
    - Symposium on trends and prospects, 7 Apr 1972 (Box 21)
    - Catholic University, 1973 (Box 21)
    - San Francisco Paper, 1973 (Box 21)
    - Hemphill Lecture, 1976 (Box 21)
    - University of Colorado, 14 Apr 1977 (Box 21)
    - Ohio State, Feb 1979 (Box 21)
    - Phi Beta Kappa at IU, 18 Apr 1979 (Box 21)
    - Annual Banquet of History of Science, 29 Dec 1979 (Box 21)
    - Intern'l conference on Christianity and Science, 23-25 Apr 1981 (Box 21)
    - W. Virginia University, 3 Mar 1983 (Box 21)
    - Annual Meeting--Am. Society of Church History, 21 Apr 1983 (Box 21)
    - Journee d'Histoire de Mathematiques, 10 Jun 1983 (Box 21)
    - Universite de Nice, 11 Jun 1983 (Box 21)
    - N.Y. Academy of Sciences, 25 Jan 1984 (Box 21)
    - DP Dinner, 18 Apr 1984 (Box 21)
    - APA materials, 26 Apr 1984 (Box 21)
    - Stanford University, 2 Oct 1984 (Box 21)
    - Haskins Lecture, 28 Dec 1984 (Box 21)
    - Alberto Coffa Memorial, 19 Jan 1985 (Box 21)
    - Annual meeting of History of Science, 3 Nov 1985 (Box 22)
    - Clagett Banquet, 25 Oct 1986 (Box 22)
    - HSS Annual meeting, Oct 1987 (Box 22)
    - Visiting Historians, Mar 1988 (Box 22)
    - Midwest Physicists Assoc., 9 Oct 1989 (Box 22)
    - HSS Brooklyn College, 13 Oct 1989 (Box 22)
    - Scott Gordon Retirement, 1989 (Box 22)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Lecture Series, 1991-1996; (Folders 8-20) (Box 22)
      - University of S. Dakota, 15 Apr 1991 (Box 22)
      - University of Missouri, 1 May 1992 (Box 22)
      - Alma College/Eastern Illinois, 29 Mar 1993; 23 Sep 1993 (Box 22)
      - Elmira College, 25 Mar 1994 (Box 22)
      - University of Michigan, 30 Mar 1994 (Box 22)
      - Lake Forest College, 13-14 Apr 1994 (Box 22)
      - Gustavus Adolphus, 2 May 1994 (Box 22)
      - University of Charleston, W. Virginia, 8 Dec 1994 (Box 22)
      - Mary Baldwin College/Kent State, 4 Apr 1995; 12 Apr 1995 (Box 22)
      - Washington & Jefferson College, 26 Apr 1995 (Box 22)
      - University of Notre Dame, 2 Apr 1996 (Box 22)
      - Jacksonville State University, 18 Apr 1996 (Box 22)
      - Phi Beta Kappa lectures, miscellaneous, 1992-1996 (Box 22)
    - Albert of Saxony Conference, 19-22 Jun 1990 (Box 22)
    - Harvard Sci-Theology Symposium (Box 22)
      - Fall 1990 (Box 22)
      - 8 Dec 1990 (Box 22)
    - History Dept. Luncheon group, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Renaissance conference, 10 Jun 1991 (Box 22)
    - Medieval Studies--IU, 6 Feb 1992 (Box 22)
    - The Taejon Expo '93, 29-30 Apr 1993 (Box 22)
    - Claremont Grad. school, 29 Oct 1993 (Box 22)
    - "Why you should believe that modern science began in the middle ages", 18 Jan 1995 (Box 22)
    - Lindberg Banquet, 27 Oct 1995 (Box 22)
    - BBC Presentation, 11 Feb 1996 (Box 22)
    - Medieval Academy of America, 11-13 Apr 1996 (Box 22)
    - Memorial Service for Richard Westfall, 6 Dec 1996 (Box 22)
    - Rice University, 14 Mar 1997; (2 folders); extref: Lecture (Box 22)
    - Scientific Revolution workshop, 18-19 Apr 1997 (Box 22)
    - Oxford University (Box 22)
      - 28 Jul 1999 (Box 22)
        General
        This file is only in digital format
      - 29 Jul 1999 (Box 22)
    - Nijmegen, The Netherlands, 16-20 Aug 1999 (Box 22)
    - Indiana University, 04 Feb 2000 (Box 22)
    - DePauw University, undated (Box 22)
  - Biographical Information
    - Honors and Awards, 1961-1982 (Box 22)
    - Listings--Who's Who in America, etc. (Box 22)
      - 1973-1990 (Box 22)
      - 1977-1982 (Box 22)
    - Copernicus Exhibit--Lilly Library, Aug-Sep 1973 (Box 22)
    - Public Appearances/Clippings, undated (Box 22)
    - Memorabilia from trip to England, 1969-1970 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Office Files, 1960-1993
    - Corresp. requesting publications devoted to history and philosophy of science, 1960 (Box 23)
    - Formation of HPS Department, 1960 (Box 23)
    - Dept. of History and Logic of Science info., 1962 (Box 23)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1963 (Box 23)
    - Equipment Committee, 1963 (Box 23)
    - Departmental Memos, 1963; 1980-1986 (Box 23)
    - HPS Minutes of Meetings, 1963-1969 (Box 23)
    - HPS Dept. Business, 1966-1969; (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Tenure Committee: History Department, 1968-1970 (Box 23)
    - Educational Policies Committee, 1969-1974 (Box 23)
    - PhD exams: History Department, 1971-1987 (Box 23)
    - University Reorganization, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Book acquisitions for HPS (Box 23)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 23)
      - 1980 (Box 23)
    - Research Committee nominations, 1980 (Box 23)
    - HPS Research Review for Office of Research and Development, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 23)
    - Book acquisitions for HPS, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Summary Report, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - Schedule of History Courses in HPS, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1982-1983 (Box 23)
    - Book acquisitions for HPS, 1983-1984 (Box 23)
    - Departmental Salaries, 1983-1984 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1983-1984 (Box 23)
    - Promotion Committee report for J. Alberto Coffa, 1983 (Box 23)
    - History Department Business, 1984-1986 (Box 23)
    - Book acquisitions for HPS, 1985-1987 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Salaries, 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - Funds from Research and Graduate Development--IU, 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - HPS Song Book, 1985 (Box 23)
    - History of Science Society Annual Meeting, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Individualized Major Program: Andy Gmerek, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1986 (Box 23)
    - Report from the Committee on Merit raises, 1986 (Box 23)
    - Undergraduate Courses in Science, Technology and Society, IUB, 1986 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report (Box 23)
      - 1988 (Box 23)
      - 1989 (Box 23)
    - Distinguished Professors Research Funds, 1990-1991 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1990 (Box 23)
    - Sabbatical Leave, 1990-1991 (Box 23)
    - Distinguished Professors Research Funds, 1991-1992 (Box 23)
    - Faculty Annual Report (Box 23)
      - 1991 (Box 23)
      - 1992 (Box 23)
      - 1993 (Box 23)
    - X207 Course Evaluation, undated (Box 23)
    - Departmental Miscellania, undated; (2 folders) (Box 23)
- Oversized Materials (legal size folders) (Box 24)
  - From Publications series: "Aristotle's Shiphaulers", 1964 (Box 24)
  - From Research for Much Ado (Box 24)
    - Walter Charleton, undated (Box 24)
    - Franciscus Bonae Spei, undated (Box 24)
    - Gratiadei, Ruvio, Javelli, undated (Box 24)
    - Jaques Le Febure, undated (Box 24)
    - Jesuit Authors, undated (Box 24)
  - From Professional Activities, Miscellaneous: Miscellaneous files, undated (Box 24)
  - IBM Cards, undated (Box 25)
    8 bundled stacks of IBM cards containing research notes.
    There is a typed key to these IBM cards to facilitate use.
  - Index Cards, undated (Box 25)
    11 bundles of index cards grouped by research topic (for example: Darwin, Medieval Science, Feudalism).